Guide to the Benjamin Newton Duke Papers, 1834-1969, bulk 1890-1929. RL.00328
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Benjamin Newton Duke papers
1834-1941, 1969 and undated
1890-1929
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke, Benjamin N. (Benjamin Newton)
RL.00328
102 Linear Feet
Benjamin Newton Duke (1855-1929) was a tobacco manufacturer, industrialist, and philanthropist of Durham, NC and New York, NY and a trustee and major benefactor of Trinity College (later Duke University). He was the son of Washington Duke, older brother of James B. Duke, husband of Sarah Pearson Angier Duke, and father of Angier Buchanan Duke and Mary Duke Biddle. The materials in this collection document the business, financial, philanthropic, and personal interests of Benjamin N. Duke and his family, especially Duke's involvement in the tobacco, textile, banking, and hydroelectric industries in North Carolina and New York and the Duke family's financial support of a variety of institutions, including educational institutions for African Americans and women, the Methodist Episcopal Church, South and individual churches, orphanages, hospitals, and community organizations. The Richard B. Arrington series and Alexander H. Sands, Jr., series document the personal and financial interests of Benjamin N. Duke's private secretaries in New York, NY.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Includes fragile letterbooks and other volumes that require consultation with staff regarding safe handling.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Benjamin Newton Duke have been received from a variety of sources over an extended period of time. While acquisition information about the bulk of the collection is unrecorded, it is believed that it was given by his daughter, Mary Duke Biddle. Additions to the collection were made by Mary Duke Biddle, 1939; Alexander H. Sands, Jr., 1940- 1941, 1953; R.D. Graham, 1950; Mrs. Lucy Cole Durham, 1951; Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans, 1961-1972, 2019; Bud Alexander, 1970; Duke University Archives, 1980; and Julia Wightman, 1990.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into nine series: Correspondence, Financial, Business, Legal, Personal, Pictures, Duke Farm (University Station, NC), Richard B. Arrington, and Alexander H. Sands, Jr.
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1855 April 27 Benjamin Newton Duke is born to Washington and Artelia Roney Duke in Orange County, North Carolina.
1858 Benjamin's mother Artelia and half-brother Sidney Taylor Duke die of typhoid fever.
1871 Benjamin and his sister Mary enroll in New Garden School (later Guilford College), near Greensboro, North Carolina.
1874 Washington Duke moves his family to Durham proper.
1877 February 21 Benjamin marries Sarah Pearson Angier of Durham, North Carolina.
1878 W. Duke, Sons and Company is established. Benjamin is a director of the new company, along with brother James B. Duke, father Washington Duke, George W. Watts, and Richard Wright.
1882 or 1883? October 3 George Washington Duke, Benjamin and Sarah's first child, is born.
1884 December 8 Angier Buchanan Duke, Benjamin and Sarah's second child, is born.
1885 September? George Washington Duke dies at age 2 or 3.
1887 November 16 Mary Lillian Duke (later Mary Duke Biddle), Benjamin and Sarah's third child, is born.
1889 Benjamin is elected to the Board of Trustees of Trinity College, Randolph County, North Carolina.
1890 Benjamin becomes a director of the newly-formed American Tobacco Company.
1891? Benjamin becomes a director of the Oxford Orphan Asylum in Oxford, North Carolina.
1892 Erwin Cotton Mills is established, with Benjamin N. Duke as president and William A. Erwin as manager.
1893 April 6 Mary E. Lyon (Mary Duke Lyon), Benjamin's sister, dies at age 39 in New York.
1893-1922 Benjamin becomes president of The Fidelity Bank of Durham, North Carolina.
1898 Benjamin serves as a delegate to the General Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, in Baltimore, Maryland.
1899? Benjamin becomes president of the Cape Fear and Northern Railway
1901 Benjamin resigns from the board of directors of the Oxford Orphan Asylum. Benjamin and Sarah purchase their first home in New York, NY. The family divides time between New York and Durham.
1902 Benjamin becomes treasurer of the American Tobacco Company
1904 Benjamin resigns as treasurer of the American Tobacco Company
1905 May 8 Washington Duke dies at age 84 in Durham, North Carolina.
1905 June Angier B. Duke graduates from Trinity College, Durham, North Carolina. Southern Power Company (later Duke Power Company) is established by Benjamin N. and brother James B. Duke in Charlotte, North Carolina.
1906 Benjamin becomes president of the Durham and Southern Railway.
1907 May Benjamin resigns as a director of the American Tobacco Company.
1907 June Mary L. Duke graduates from Trinity College, Durham, North Carolina.
1908-1910 Benjamin and Sarah's "Four Acres" house is built in Durham, North Carolina.
1913 April Richard B. Arrington, Benjamin and James's private secretary and financial agent dies in White Plains, New York. Alexander H. Sands, Jr., is hired as Benjamin and James's private secretary and financial agent in New York, New York.
1915 Angier B. Duke marries Cordelia Biddle. Mary L. Duke marries Anthony J. Drexel Biddle, Jr.
1922 Benjamin resigns from the presidency of The Fidelity Bank of Durham, NC
1923 September 3 Angier B. Duke dies in a boating accident on Long Island Sound at the age of 38.
1925 Benjamin and Sarah establish the Angier B. Duke Memorial to support scholarship at Duke University.
1925 October 10 James B. Duke dies at the age of 68 in New York, New York.
1927 Benjamin resigns from the presidency of Erwin Cotton Mills Benjamin resigns from the presidency of Durham and Southern Railway
1927 January 8 Benjamin dies in New York, New York at the age of 71 and is interred in the Duke family mausoleum in Maplewood Cemetery, Durham, North Carolina
1936 The remains of Benjamin, James B. Duke, and Washington Duke are removed from Maplewood Cemetery to the Memorial Chapel of Duke University Chapel.
1936 September 3 Sarah P. Duke dies at the age of 80 in Blowing Rock, North Carolina.
Benjamin Newton Duke (1855-1929) was a tobacco manufacturer, industrialist, and philanthropist of Durham, NC and New York, NY and a trustee and major benefactor of Trinity College (later Duke University). He was the son of Washington Duke, older brother of James B. Duke, husband of Sarah Pearson Angier Duke, and father of Angier Buchanan Duke and Mary Duke Biddle.
Benjamin Newton Duke held a leadership position in several North Carolina and New York businesses, including the American Tobacco Company, W. Duke, Sons & Company, Erwin Cotton Mills, Fidelity Bank of Durham, Citizens' National Bank of Durham, Trinity Land Company, Durham Realty Corporation, Durham and Southern Railway Company, and Southern Power Company. Along with James B. Duke and their partner, George Washington Watts, Benjamin Duke held substantial investments in a variety of enterprises throughout the United States.
Duke was also the primary agent for the Duke family's philanthropic activities from the late 1880s until his death.
Related Material
Board of Trustees Records, 1860-ongoing, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Duke Family papers, 1885-1992 (bulk 1892-1927), David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
James Buchanan Duke Papers, 1777-1999 and undated, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Washington Duke Papers, 1764-1987, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Erwin Cotton Mills Records, 1832-1976, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
William Preston Few Records and Papers, 1814-1971 and undated (bulk 1911-1940), Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Robert Lee Flowers Records, 1891-1968, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
John C. Kilgo Records and Papers, 1888-1970 (bulk 1894-1920), Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
W. Duke, Sons & Co. Advertising Materials, 1880-1910, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Semans Family Papers, 1878-2008 and undated, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Collection Overview
The papers of Benjamin Newton Duke have been collected from various sources over time and span the years 1834 to 1969, although the bulk of the material dates from 1890 to 1929. The materials in the collection document the business, financial, philanthropic, and personal interests of Benjamin N. Duke and his family in Durham, NC and New York, NY, especially Duke's involvement in the tobacco, textile, banking, and hydroelectric industries and the Duke family's financial support of a variety of institutions, including educational institutions for African Americans and women, the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, and individual churches, orphanages, hospitals, and community organizations. Types of material in the collection include correspondence, financial statements and ledgers, bills and receipts, architectural blueprints and drawings, land plats, deeds, photographs, photograph albums, scrapbooks, and a diary.
Family members represented include Sarah P. Duke, Angier Buchanan Duke, Mary Duke Biddle, Washington Duke, James B. Duke, Brodie L. Duke, Lida Duke Angier, and Anthony J. Drexel Biddle, Jr. Other individuals represented include Julian S. Carr, William A. Erwin, John C. Kilgo, William P. Few, Daniel Lindsay Russell, James E. Shepard, and George W. Watts.
The Richard B. Arrington series and Alexander H. Sands, Jr. series document the personal and financial interests of Benjamin N. Duke's private secretaries in New York, NY.
Industries -- North Carolina; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Women's colleges -- North Carolina; Water-power -- South Carolina; Water-power -- North Carolina; Businessmen -- North Carolina -- Durham; Capitalists and financiers -- United States; Orphanages -- North Carolina; Philanthropists -- North Carolina; Railroads -- North Carolina; Universities and colleges -- North Carolina; Textile industry -- North Carolina; Electric utilities -- North Carolina; Tobacco industry -- North Carolina; Banks and banking -- North Carolina; Photographs; Duke family; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.); Duke, Sarah Pearson Angier, 1856-1936; Methodist Episcopal Church, South; Duke University; Duke, Washington, 1820-1905; Sands, Alexander H., 1891-1960; Duke, James Buchanan, 1856-1925; American Tobacco Company; Biddle, Anthony Joseph Drexel, 1896-1961; Arrington, Richard B., d. 1913; Biddle, Mary Duke, 1887-1960; Erwin Cotton Mills; Duke, Angier Buchanan, 1884-1923; Duke, Benjamin N. (Benjamin Newton); W. Duke, Sons & Co.
- Correspondence, 1871-1941 and undated; 1893-1923; 37.5 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  The letters, memoranda, telegrams, invoices, receipts, printed reports and other items comprising this series document the financial, philanthropic, and personal interests of Benjamin N. Duke and his family. Duke family members represented in the series include Sarah P. Duke, Washington Duke, Angier B. Duke, Mary L. Duke (Mary Duke Biddle), Lida Duke Angier, Brodie L. Duke, James B. Duke, and Anthony J. Drexel Biddle, Jr. Other correspondents include John C. Angier, John S. Bassett, Warren A. Candler, Julian S. Carr, John F. Crowell, J. B. Cobb, Warren C. Coleman, Ceasar Cone, William A. Erwin, William P. Few, Robert L. Flowers, C. P. H. Gilbert, Jonathan R. Hawkins, L. L. Hobbs, Charles C. Hook, N. M. Jurney, J. C. Kilgo, W. S. Lee, John Merrick, Solomon Pool, Jeter C. Pritchard, Daniel Lindsay Russell, Thomas Settle, James E. Shepard, James H. Southgate, Andrew P. Tyer, and George W. Watts. Many of the letters were addressed to or written by Benjamin N. Duke's financial agents and secretaries in Durham, NC and New York, NY, including James E. Stagg, Richard B. Arrington, Elizabeth A. Childs, and Alexander H. Sands, Jr.
  The series provides a particularly rich history of Benjamin Duke's relationship with Trinity College, documenting his role on the Board of Trustees, Executive Committee, and Building Committee as well as his financial support during and after the institution's relocation to Durham from Randolph County. There are letters to and from trustees, faculty, students, and representatives of the Methodist Church regarding the administration and financial support of the college; letters from students or their parents requesting financial assistance to attend the college; exchanges with architects and contractors regarding the design and construction of campus buildings; applications to teach for the college; and correspondence with faculty related to non-college topics, such as loans, investments, property transactions, and personal matters.
  The series also documents Benjamin Duke and his family's other philanthropic activities, including their support of educational institutions for African-Americans and women, the Methodist Episcopal Church, South and individual churches, and social welfare agencies and community organizations, including orphanages and hospitals. Individual institutions represented include Elon College, Greensboro Female College, Granbery College, Guilford College, Kittrell College, Lincoln Memorial University, Louisburg Female College, the National Religious Training School and Chautauqua for the Colored Race, the New Bern Industrial and Collegiate Institute, the North Carolina College for Negroes (later North Carolina Central University), Rutherford College, Southern Conservatory of Music, Trinity College, the Bingham School, and Durham Graded Schools; Main Street Methodist Church, Duke Memorial Methodist Church, Trinity Methodist Church, and West Durham Methodist Church; North Carolina Children's Home, Oxford Orphan Asylum, Lincoln Hospital, Watts Hospital, the YMCA and YWCA of Durham, NC, and the Salvation Army.
  Major industries represented in the series include tobacco, cotton and textiles, hydroelectric power, banking, mining, railroads, and real estate. Much of the business-related correspondence concerns financial matters such as notices of dividend payments and requests for stockholder subscriptions. Individual companies include the American Tobacco Company, W. Duke, Sons & Company, Asheville Cotton Mills, Cannon Manufacturing Company, Coleman Manufacturing Company, Commonwealth Cotton Manufacturing Company, Durham Cotton Manufacturing Company, Erwin Cotton Mills, Leaksville Cotton Mills, Locke Cotton Mills, Odell Manufacturing Company, Proximity Manufacturing Company, Kerr Bag Manufacturing Company, Roxboro Cotton Mills, Spray Water and Power Company, Durham Electric Lighting Company, Southern Power Company, Fidelity Bank of Durham, Citizen's National Bank of Durham, Durham and Southern Railway, Cape Fear and Northern Railway, Cary Lumber Company, Alaska Power and Dredging Company, Jim Butler Tonopah Mining Company, Seward Dredging Company, Virginia-Carolina Chemical Company, Durham Realty Corporation, Trinity Land Company, and the National Drama Corporation.
  Correspondence related to the tobacco industry includes letters from executives and directors of the American Tobacco Company and its subsidiaries, including W. Duke, Sons & Company. Also included are letters from department and branch managers, legal counsel, leaf brokers and dealers, investors, merchants and salespeople, and individuals seeking employment. There is extensive correspondence between 1892 and 1902 regarding the state of the tobacco markets in North Carolina and Virginia, as well as purchases of tobacco, cutters, wrappers, and other supplies. Correspondence related to official American Tobacco Company business consists mainly of arrangements for meetings of the Board of Directors and details of investments made on behalf of the company and its executives. Also included are general updates from W. W. Fuller on legal suits faced by the company and arrangements for the conversion of American Tobacco Company stock after the dissolution of the trust.
  Letters related to the textiles and hydroelectric power industries include extensive correspondence with William A. Erwin regarding the establishment, funding, operations, and expansion of the Erwin Cotton Mills. Also present are letters related to the surveying of water power sites in North Carolina and South Carolina and purchases of properties and water rights prior to the establishment of the Southern Power Company.
  Arrangement
  The Correspondence series is arranged in two subseries according to format: Letters and Letterbooks.
  Related Materials
  Correspondence with financial brokers is found in the Financial series, Investments subseries.
  Correspondence between Benjamin N. Duke and others regarding Duke's effort to identify and financially assist extended family members is located in the James Buchanan Duke papers, Correspondence series, 1924-1925.
  - Letters, 1872-1941
    Scope and Contents
    The Letters subseries contains primarily inbound correspondence addressed to Benjamin N. Duke. After 1905, there is an increased volume of copies of outgoing correspondence written by Duke's secretaries, much of which duplicates the correspondence found in the Letterbook subseries.
    The letters are arranged chronologically.
    - 1872, 1877, 1879, 1 folders (Box 1)
      Includes a letter from Benjamin N. Duke to a New Garden School classmate and letters from George F. Wardle (agent for W. Duke, Sons & Company).
    - 1880, 1883, 1885, 1886, 1889, 1 folders (Box 1)
    - 1890 March-December and undated, 1 folders (Box 1)
    - 1891, 13 folders (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence with George S. Prichard regarding details of their tobacco purchasing agreement; a letter from Brodie L. Duke about his visit to England; a letter from Julian S. Carr discussing a proposal for an industrial school for girls in Durham; a letter from John Pope with a list of tobacco buyers and salaries for various markets of the American Tobacco Company for the year 1891.
    - 1892, 15 folders (Box 2)
      Includes correspondence and statement regarding a dispute between Julian S. Carr and B.N. Duke over claims made about the American Tobacco Company; and a statement comparing cigarette sales for branches of the American Tobacco Company from April 1891 to April 1892.
    - 1893 January-September, 16 folders (Box 3)
      Includes letters related to the death of Mary E. Lyon (Mary Duke Lyon) and the design and construction of the Duke family mausoleum.
    - 1893 October-1894 July, 19 folders (Box 4)
    - 1894 August-1895 March, 16 folders (Box 5)
      Includes correspondence related to the "New Jersey suit" and labor and cigarette legislation.
    - 1895 April-November, 16 folders (Box 6)
    - 1895 December-1896 May, 16 folders (Box 7)
      Includes correspondence with Thomas Settle regarding cigarette and antitrust legislation and the need for a new public building in Durham; and letters from W. T. Blackwell seeking financial assistance and investment advice.
    - 1896 June-December, 15 folders (Box 8)
      Includes James E. Shepard's proposal for building an African-American teaching college in Durham; letters from Daniel Lindsay Russell and others regarding 1896 Republican campaigns and the Fusion movement in North Carolina; and letters related to Washington Duke's endowment of Trinity College.
    - 1897 January-September, 18 folders (Box 9)
      Includes correspondence related to the funding and construction of the [Mary E. Duke Lyon] Memorial Hall at Guilford College.
    - 1897 October-1898 May, 15 folders (Box 10)
    - 1898 June-December, 14 folders (Box 11)
      Includes letters from Governor Daniel Lindsay Russell about the Fusion movement, the 1898 election campaigns of North Carolina and their results, and personal and political troubles following the November 1898 Wilmington race riots; and a letter from Bishop W. A. Candler requesting aid for missionary work in Cuba (1898 August).
    - 1899 January-July, 15 folders (Box 12)
      Includes letters regarding fundraising for the Braxton Craven Memorial Hall at Trinity College (1899 January); the rebuilding of the Durham Colored Graded School after a fire (1899 January-February); the construction of a Methodist church in Havana, Cuba; a letter from Julian S. Carr regarding the need for new management at the Durham Electric Lighting Company; and correspondence related to the debt of Daniel Lindsay Russell.
    - 1899 August-December, 12 folders (Box 13)
      Includes correspondence related to the Southern Conservatory of Music (Durham, NC) building addition and the purchase of timber land in Florida.
    - 1899 September 14, oversize watercolor and pencil sketches (Box 123, Folder 3)
      Chas. C. Hook to J. E. Stagg, sketches of Southern Conservatory of Music addition.
    - circa 1890s, 1 folders (Box 13)
    - 1900 January, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - 1900 February-October, 17 folders (Box 14)
      Includes letters related to construction of B.N. Duke's stables (Durham, NC) and J. C. Kilgo residence; dedication of the Southern Conservatory of Music; Catawba River water power; Erwin Cotton Mills expansion; and state and national Republican campaigns; and a letter from J.S. Trice regarding the Soudan Mission in Sierra Leone (1900 March).
    - 1900 November-1901 April, 15 folders (Box 15)
      Includes correspondence related to the Gattis vs. Kilgo trial and appeal; Cooleemee Cotton Mills; Coleman Manufacturing Company; the endowment of Lincoln Hospital (Durham, NC); the Furches and Douglas impeachment trials (North Carolina legislature); the Guilford Battleground Commission; and the purchase of a house on 5th Ave. in New York, NY. Also includes letters (1900 December-1901 January) from Moses H. Cone regarding the sale of his finishing works; and a letter from W. B. Lee (1901 April) describing work at the Colégio Americano Granbery.
    - 1901 May-October, 14 folders (Box 16)
      Includes letters regarding the Duke family's relocation to New York; the construction of the Trinity College library; the Gattis vs. Kilgo case; correspondence from W. A. Erwin regarding expenses from water power surveys in North Carolina; and a letter from Ceasar Cone relating his interest in establishing a cotton mill in South Carolina.
    - 1901 November-1902 March, 17 folders (Box 17)
      Includes correspondence related to water power surveys in North Carolina and South Carolina and a letter from James B. Duke to B.N. Duke regarding his trip to Russia (1902 January).
    - 1902 April-August, 16 folders (Box 18)
      Includes letters related to the Erwin Mill No. 2 site in Harnett County, NC; NC and SC water power surveys; and a letter from Minnie Duke concerning her husband Brodie L. Duke (1902 April).
    - 1902 September-December, 12 folders (Box 19)
      Includes letters related to the funding needs of Watts Hospital and Kittrell College; letters from W. A. Erwin about the new Erwin Cotton Mills sites in Cooleemee, NC and Harnett County, NC; letters from William A. Blair, Lindsay Patterson, and Jeter C. Pritchard on 1902 political campaigns; and letters related to Benjamin N. Duke's purchase of property on 5th Avenue and 76th Street, New York, NY.